Dad, Minmin is right.
爸 珉敏说得对
They are her friends...
这都是她朋友
You call those friends?
这些算朋友吗
And you,
还有你
making friends with Japanese?
还认识日本朋友啊
I... I don't know any.
我 我不认识啊
Don't lie to me.
你可别骗我
I... I really... I really don't know.
我 我真 我真不认识
Someone was
刚才有个人
asking for Meng Duoci or something.
找什么孟什么多慈的
Dad,
爸爸
how do you know about Meng Duoci?
你怎么知道孟多慈
I don't know any Meng Duoci.
我哪认识什么孟多慈啊
Someone came earlier,
刚才有个人来
first asking for your brother,
一会儿找你哥
then you,
一会儿又找你
claiming to know Meng Duoci or something,
还认识什么孟什么多慈
sounded like a Japanese to me.
一听就是个东洋鬼子嘛
Yuansheng,
远生
what's going on?
怎么回事儿
Li Qiushi is Meng Duoci.
黎秋实就是孟多慈
She's the daughter of the couple
她就是文华饭店
who were victimized at the Van Hwa Hotel.
遇害那家人的女儿
Besides me
这件事情
and Chen Hao,
除了我和陈浩之外
only the killer knows it.
只有凶手知道
Hongfa,
鸿发
the killer
你说那个凶手
attacked Miss Luo
都给骆警官打成那样了
and is still looking for her.
还来找骆警官
What does he want?
他到底想干什么呀
Who cares what he wants.
管他想干什么
We'll guard the Luo's home tonight.
今天晚上就守好骆家
Even if he turned into a fly,
他就是变成苍蝇
we would not let him in.
也不能让它飞进去
Can you tell me
你能不能告诉我
what exactly happened?
到底发生了什么事儿
Nothing.
没事儿
What's with
这一大帮的人
all these people?
干什么呢
Are you planning to stay the night?
晚上赖在这儿不走了
No, that won't happen.
那 那不会
They'll leave soon.
一会儿就走
You just relax and rest.
您就踏踏实实休息就行
Sister,
姐
you said before,
之前你说
officers from the Fourth House took good care of you.
四所人都很照顾你
I thought
我还以为
you were just comforting Dad and brother.
是你安慰爸爸和哥哥的
But now,
你看现在
some keep a lookout in front,
前面有人看着
others guard at the back door.
后面有人守着
They really
大家真的都在
are protecting us.
保护我们呢
They do
看来他们是
care about you.
真的很关心你
Alright,
行啦
get some sleep.
早点睡觉吧
I'm not hungry, thank you.
我不饿 谢谢
I'm not hungry either.
我也不饿
But I've heard
不过我听说
that when you're tired,
人困的时候啊
eating something can perk you up.
吃点儿东西能提提神
Thanks.
谢谢
Is your brother doing well
你弟弟在外面
with his work outside?
干活还顺利吗
He's doing fine.
挺好
He works as
平时在印刷厂
a typesetter in a printing factory.
给人当排字工人
On Sundays,
星期天呢
he helps out in a bookstore.
去书店帮人卖卖书
All the jobs were obtained
都是队长托关系
through the Captain's connections.
帮他找的差事
Apologize to him for me.
替我跟他说声抱歉
If it weren't for me cutting in line,
如果不是因为我插队
he should have been a policeman
他现在应该在四所
at the Fourth House by now.
当警察
Actually...
其实
my brother doesn't want to be a policeman.
其实我弟他不想当警察
He's not like me.
他跟我不一样
He enjoys reading
他平时就喜欢看看文章
and took to streets, protesting and chanting
跟一群大学生
slogans alongside college students.
上街闹游行喊口号
I don't really understand
我也不懂
these young people's stuff.
他们年轻人那些事儿
But I've come to realize,
不过我算是想明白了
everyone has their own life to live.
一人一命
Let them do what they want.
想干什么干什么吧
You're doing a great job
你这警察呀
as a police officer.
当得挺好
Captain!
队长
Erbai!
二白
Did you find the place?
查到地方了
Yes, I did. The emblem is a school crest,
查到了 图案是校徽
run by the Japanese in Hongkou District.
日本人在虹口办的学校
Let's discuss
具体情况
the details back at the station.
咱们回四所再说
What are you doing here?
你们怎么在这儿
A Japanese man
昨天来个日本人
came by yesterday.
找上门了
We thought he might be the killer,
我们怕是凶手
so we kept watch here overnight.
就在这儿守了一夜
Alright, let's head back.
行 先回四所
You two keep watch here.
你们俩在这儿守着
Okay, let's go.
好 走 走
Let's move.
走
What... what did you find out?
查 查出什么来了
You nearly lost your life,
命都差点儿丢了
and you still want to be a police officer?
你还想回去当警察
I just don't understand
我就想不明白了
why you're so keen
到底为什么
on going back to the police?
那么想回去当警察
Initially,
我一开始
I wanted to become a police officer
想要当警察
to chase away those
是因为想要赶走那些
who troubled my brother.
找哥哥麻烦的人
I thought that by wearing the uniform,
我以为穿上警服
I would be a cop.
我就是警察了
I just wanted to protect
我就是想保护那些
those I could.
我可以保护的人
But later, I realized
但是后来发现
I was far from being a real cop.
我离真正的警察还很远
And I thought,
我也以为
like everything else
我会像从小到大
I've done since my childhood,
做所有事情那样
even though I became a police officer,
虽然我当了警察
I would
也会成为
be the worst
警察里当得
one again.
最不好的那一个
Yet,
可是
surprisingly, someone say I'm pretty good at it,
居然有人说我很厉害
and he says
还说
it's not about ability.
这和能力高低无关
So you've made up your mind?
所以你就铁了心了
I stayed up
昨天
last night, thinking.
我想了一夜
I think
我想
it's not about whether or not
这和当不当警察
I'm a cop,
没有关系
but about
而是和我想
what kind of person I want to become.
成为什么样子的人有关
Maybe
也许
I'd never be a heroic,
我永远也没有办法成为
justice-serving officer
像队长那样
like the Captain,
匡扶正义厉害的警察
and maybe one day,
甚至有一天
I won't even be a cop.
我就不当警察了
But,
但是我想
at least I should be
我至少应该成为
someone useful.
一个有用的人
Dad,
爸爸
for the first time in my life
在四所这段时间
when I worked at the Fourth House,
我第一次觉得
I felt I could become a person like that.
我可以成为这样子的人
I don't know
我不知道
if it's an illusion,
是不是我的错觉
but I feel like the officers
我觉得四所的人
kind of like me,
都还挺喜欢我的
and I like them, too.
而且我也喜欢他们
This is the first time
爸爸还是头一回
I've heard you speak so earnestly
听你这么认真地
about one thing.
说一件事情
So, Dad,
那爸爸
have you agreed with me?
你同意我回去了
In my heart,
在爸爸的心里
I would never agree
永远都不可能
to let you go back.
同意你回去
It is ridiculous indeed.
我就奇了怪了
Can't your station
你们四所
recruit any other female officers?
是招不到女警吗
A bunch of people at my doorstep day and night for you.
成天一堆人守着你
Even if they worried about your safety,
就算是担心你
they should know you are protected by
咱们家里也不是没人哪
your brother and I.
还有我跟你哥呢
They don't even go home and
一堆人守着你还不回家
just guard you.
就守着你个大傻丫头
Dad.
爸爸
I'm being very serious
我现在在很严肃地
with you right now.
跟你说这个问题
I know, very, very serious.
我知道 特别特别严肃
Finally.
什么时候了
Why so late?
才过来
Someone called in this morning.
一早有人打电话报警
The mahjong parlor owner
麻将馆的老板
was found hanged.
被人给吊死了
What's the name of the mahjong parlor?
麻将馆叫什么
He Yi.
合意
That place is not far from Miss Luo's home.
那地方离骆警官家不远
And
这还没完呢
A clerk from Dongguang pawnshop
东光当铺的伙计
was shot dead.
被人开枪给打死了
Looks like we've got our work cut out!
又有得忙了
Weren't you suspended?
你不是被停职了吗
Who allowed him to come?
谁让他来的
Chief,
所长
there's something important
有个重要的事情
I need to report.
跟你汇报
You! Get out!
你出去 你
Here's the thing,
是这样啊
now, the situation is...
现在事情是
Why am I being kicked out?
把我给撵出来了
What's going on?
干什么
You'll regret this!
造反啊
I found it out
我在服装厂的
in the clothing factory's order book
订单样图上查到
that the uniform
那套校服
is for the Japanese Youth
是日本青年实业学校的
Industrial School.
校服
This means our target
也就是说目标很有可能
is likely
就是这所学校
a student there.
里面的学生
He has an accomplice
他还有一名同党
named Hideo Yoshida.
叫做吉田英夫
I suspect they're using false identities
我怀疑他们的身份
to disguise themselves,
也是为了掩人耳目
possibly having other aliases.
还有别的身份
The two homicide cases
刚刚老左说了
Ronghua just mentioned
另外两起命案
may be connected to the two suspects.
很有可能跟他们有关
I called and found out
我刚才打电话过去问了
the school
现在学校
only holds classes
只有下午到晚上有课
from 2 PM
下午是两点开门
to 7 PM.
晚上最晚到七点
Today, however, the school is closed for a holiday.
但是今天学校放假了
Classes will resume tomorrow.
明天才正常上课
Let's make our move tomorrow then.
那我们明天再动手
The school is located in Hongkou District,
学校的位置在虹口区
near the Suzhou Creek,
靠着苏州河
surrounded by a large Japanese expatriate area,
周围是大片的日侨区
which is at our disadvantage.
环境对我们非常不利
We need to lure the target
我们必须要把目标
into a smaller side street
引到小路上
to take action.
才能动手
It's still early morning,
今天时间还早
and you were up all night.
昨晚都没睡
Go get some sleep for now.
都早点回去休息
Captain!
队长
Look who's here.
你看谁来了
Mr. Luo.
骆先生
You watched over
你们在我家
my house last night.
窝了一夜
Now that Minmin
现在珉敏呢
is coming back,
要回来
I'm worried you might be hungry
我怕你们饿坏了
and wouldn't be able to look after her well.
照顾不好她
Tianxiang, Qinqin.
天祥 勤芹
Here's some breakfast I prepared for you.
这是给你们准备的早饭
Everyone, eat up!
大家快吃吧
My Dad
我爸爸做了
made six portions,
一二三四五六份呢
all are my favorite food.
都是我从小爱吃的
Thank you, Mr. Luo.
谢谢骆先生
Thanks, Mr. Luo.
谢谢骆叔
Aren't you suspended?
您不是停职了吗
Oh,
对了
and you,
还有你
didn't you quit?
你不是不当警察了吗
Yuansheng is staying.
向警官他不走了
That's right.
对 叔
Yuansheng is staying,
向警官不走了
and Miss Luo is back.
骆警官这也回来了
No one is absent.
我们这四所又齐了
Here's your uniform.
这个是警服
I wasn't going to give it to you,
本来不打算给你
but I know
但是我知道
I can't lock you up...
爸锁不住你
not that it means I agree...
但不代表同意
Not that it means you agree I should be a cop.
不代表同意我当警察
So,
所以
I'll remember more than ever
我会更加时刻记住
to take care of myself.
我要保护好自己
Thank you, dad.
谢谢爸爸
Be home on time every night.
晚上按时回家
I will.
一定
She will.
会的
It's okay.
没事儿没事儿
Eat while it's hot.
趁热吃啊
Get home early.
早点儿回家
Mr. Luo, take care.
骆先生慢走
Captain,
队长
Officer Luo Minmin requests to return to duty!
警员骆珉敏请求归队
Welcome back!
欢迎回来
Yeah!
好
Hurry, come eat!
快快快
Come on, eat up.
快过来吃
Try it.
来来来 快吃
Make sure to have some dough sticks.
一定要多吃这个油条
I can
这个油条
eat two every morning!
我每天早上能吃两个
And let me introduce
还有这个糖油饼
these sugar pastries.
我给你们特别介绍一下
The sesame on top is very fragrant,
这上面的芝麻特别香
and the sugar inside is crunchy.
而且里面的糖都是脆的
It smells so good!
太香了
I could smell it
我来的路上
on my way here!
就闻见这个味了
This tastes so good!
太香了
What else?
还有什么
Try this pastry.
哥你尝尝这个饼
It's so good.
太好吃了
Save some for Ronghua.
给老左留份
Sure thing.
好嘞好嘞
Don't just serve.
你别顾着分了
Eat some yourself.
你自己也吃嘛
Eat up.
快吃
Slow down.
慢点儿 慢点儿
Don't get choked.
别噎着了
You should try mine.
哥你尝尝我这个
So good!
真香
I... I don't want yours.
我 我不尝你这个
Tell you what,
我跟你们说
when I was little,
我从小吃我爸爸做的饭
I couldn't
之后
eat anyone else's cook.
谁家的饭我都吃不下
My Dad's cooking is the best.
就我爸爸做的饭最好吃
How about you come over to eat
回头请你们去我家吃饭
at my place sometime?
怎么样
Sure.
行
Come on, Yuansheng.
来 向警官
Ronghua!
老左
I'm not the Chief.
我不是所长
You are.
你才是所长呢
You're the boss here.
你是哥 你是所长
It's you.
你是
I've got good news.
跟你说个好消息啊
Minmin is back.
珉敏归队了
She and her Dad brought breakfast,
她跟她爸带了早饭
and I got a portion for you.
给你拿了一份
Is she okay?
她没事儿了
She's fine.
没事儿
Are you still upset?
你还生气呢
She's fine, but what about you?
她没事儿 你呢
You've been suspended.
都停职了
What are you still doing here?
你说你 你还混什么混
Whatever I say, you won't listen.
怎么说你都不听
Why not reconsider
要不你再考虑考虑
that bodyguard job with Mr. Jin?
上次那金老板那保镖
I think it's a
我觉得那差事
good gig, right?
挺好的是吧
What are you doing?
干什么
You startled me.
一惊一乍的
Wishing you a safe journey.
但愿你一路平安
May your bridges be strong
桥都坚固
and tunnels be bright.
隧道都光明
Having not
一别数日
seen my old friend for days,
不知老友是否安好
Here's a poem to express my thoughts.
赠诗一首表我牵挂之心
If it suits you,
若时间方便
let us meet at the usual time and place
请于本月二十六日
on the 26th this month.
老时间 老地方相见
Come on, chase me!
来呀 来追我呀
Wait for me!
等等我
Hurry up.
快过来
Do you like poetry?
你喜欢读诗吗
I've read Taranci's "Train."
只读过塔朗吉的《火车》
Do you know
那你知道
what it says
写在车头上那一句
on the locomotive?
是什么吗
May your bridges be strong
愿你桥都坚固
and tunnels be bright.
隧道都光明
That's the code phrase
这是我和邓先生的
Mr. Deng and I used.
固定接头方式
I used to wait here with an umbrella
以前我都会拿着伞
at this time for him.
这个时间在这儿等他
But I never expected
但实在没想到
it would be you today.
今天是你
After the leader was arrested,
组长被捕之后
the CPC assigned
组织把重新
me to
唤醒你的任务
re-activate you.
交给了我
From now on,
从现在开始
I'll be your superior,
我就是你的新上线
taking over from Leader Deng,
以后就由我接替邓组长
and I'll be your direct contact.
和你单线联系
Is Deng okay?
组长还好吗
He's detained
他被关在
at the Shanghai Garrison Command.
淞沪警备司令部
He communicated
这个接头的方式
the code phrase to me.
就是他托组织告诉我的
Besides re-activating you,
今天除了重新唤醒你
there's another thing today.
还有另外一件事情
This photo was taken by a journalist
这张照片是救国会
from the national salvation organization.
一名记者拍下的
On the right, you know him well,
右边这个你很熟悉
the Deputy Chief of the Public Security Bureau, Tan Shiyuan.
公安局副局长谭施远
The man on the left holding a wine glass
左边这个拿酒杯的男人
is unidentified,
还不清楚身份
and the one in the middle is Nakamura Naoki.
中间这个叫里见直树
He runs a charitable hall
他在上海经营一间
in Shanghai called Hongji Benevolent Society
叫弘济善堂的慈善堂
and
而且
has been awarded a good citizen
被上海公安局评过
for abiding by the law.
遵纪守法的好市民
Tan Shiyuan even
谭施远给他
presented him with a medal,
颁奖章的时候
which was reported in newspapers.
还登过报纸
I remember that news.
这条新闻我记得
The police are often dispatched
弘济善堂门口
to maintain order in front of
经常有警察过去
the Hongji Benevolent Society.
维持难民的秩序
Feng Guangyun dispatches all.
都是冯广云派去的人
The national salvation organization found
救国会发现这个地方
that ronin frequents the site,
有浪人出入
suspecting
怀疑他们在进行
espionage activities.
间谍活动
The organization
所以托组织
asked for help in investigating
帮忙调查
Nakamura Naoki's identity.
里见直树的身份
And,
结果
we found that
我们查到
this Japanese
这个日本人
was formerly a part of the Kwantung Army's
曾经在关东军
fourth section,
第四课任职
responsible for military propaganda.
负责军中宣传
He managed
哈尔滨大观园的
the propaganda efforts
宣抚工作
at Harbin Daguanyuan.
就是他主持的
Nakamura also
而且这个里见
represented
还曾经代表
the South Manchuria Railway office in Nanjing,
满铁驻南京事务所
selling railway equipment
向南京政府
to the Nanjing government,
推销铁道车辆器材
gaining deep trust from the Japanese military.
深得日本军方信任
Are you saying
你的意思是
Tan Shiyuan is colluding with the Japanese military
谭施远通过里见直树
through Nakamura Naoki?
勾结日本军方
Exactly.
对
This relates to the Meng family homicide.
这关系到孟家的凶杀案
I know you and Xiang Yuansheng
我知道你跟向远生
have been investigating it.
一直在调查
Just today, we made a progress.
今天刚有新的进展
We suspect the killer
我们怀疑凶手是
is a student from the Japanese Youth
日本青年实业学校的
Industrial School.
学生
We plan to stake out
准备明天下午
their school gate tomorrow afternoon.
去他们学校门口守着
If the suspect is indeed from there,
如果是那儿的学生
we will catch him tomorrow.
明天一定抓到他
I've always suspected
我也一直怀疑
that Mr. Meng and Mrs. Meng's murder
孟先生和孟太太被害
was connected to the Japanese military.
和日本军方有关
But now with Tan Shiyuan's collusion
但是现在谭施远
with the Japanese,
勾结日本人
if you hand over the murderer to police authority,
如果通过警察逮捕凶手
Tan will eventually
最终谭施远
let them escape punishment.
也会让他们逃脱制裁
That's why
所以
I need you to hand the person over to me.
你一定要把人交给我
That's also why
这也是今天
I needed to see you today.
我为什么找你的原因
Another thing,
还有一件事情要告诉你
the leader refused
组长拒绝了
our rescue plan
组织的营救计划
because he didn't want
因为他不希望
more comrades to risk their lives for him.
再有人为他而冒险
Soon,
很快
he'll be transferred
他就会被转到
to the Central Military Prison in Nanjing.
南京军人中央监狱
What then?
然后呢
Activating you was the last request
启用你是组长向组织
the leader made to the CPC.
提出的最后一个申请
He didn't have anything to give you,
他没有东西要给你
but he gave you
但他把自己的代号
his code name.
给了你
From now on,
从现在开始
you are 037.
你就是零三七
Leader,
组长
I have one more question.
我还有个问题
When I'm officially activated,
等我被正式启用那一天
will I also have a code name,
我是不是也有个代号
like your 037?
就像您那零三七一样
Of course.
当然
You will.
当然会
You are a good policeman,
你是个好警察
Chen Hao.
陈浩
Being a policeman
警察对于你来讲
isn't just your disguise.
不仅仅是保护色
It's also your dream.
也是你的梦想
I know
我知道
you are a person with dreams.
你是个心中有梦的人
I once asked Mr. Deng
以前我问过邓先生
if I would get
当我被正式
a new code name
启用的那一天
when I was activated.
会不会也有个新的代号
Now I have one,
现在有了
but I never thought it would be this one.
但没想到是这一个
If anyone
如果有人还能
could see Mr. Deng again,
再见到邓先生
please tell him
请帮我转达
that I will complete my mission.
我陈浩一定完成好任务
Let's hope the operation goes smoothly.
希望行动一切顺利吧
Thank you, Yuansheng.
谢谢远生哥哥
Come on,
走
go test my battleship.
去水坑试试我的军舰去
Let's go.
走喽
Sorry, Captain Chen.
不好意思陈队长
Sorry for the trouble.
添麻烦了
It's nothing.
没事儿
Let's go.
我们走
He cries every time he visits.
他每次来每次都哭
You really like ships, huh?
你很喜欢船啊
I do.
喜欢
I even thought
我还想过
maybe one day
也许有一天
I could be a warship captain.
我能够当上舰长
But I never imagined
但没想过
that one day I'd be sitting here,
有一天我会坐在这里
folding paper boats for kids.
给一群小孩折纸船
You've changed after joining
你和刚来四所的时候
the Fourth House.
不太一样
Haven't you changed, too?
你不也变了吗
Me?
我
Fixing that broken lock today
坏了这么久的门锁
after so long?
今天突然想起来要修
I used to live an unshaped life.
以前活得太潦草
Today marks a fresh start.
今天算是重新开始
Plus,
还有
you're moving in, right?
这不你要搬进来了吗
I thought I should tidy up the place.
把屋子收拾得像样点
If we manage
今天如果能够
to catch the killer today,
顺利抓到凶手
this case will be closed,
事情就结束了
and I should head back to Nanjing.
我也该回南京了
But before I go,
但是走之前
I need to see
我一定要亲眼看见
that person sentenced,
那个人被判刑
to fulfill the promise I made to Qiushi
也算是兑现了我给秋实
and the person
还有托我来上海
who sent me to Shanghai.
那个人的承诺
Pleasure working with you.
合作愉快
Hope it all goes well.
一切顺利
Shine your shoes, sir?
擦个鞋啊老板
Yes.
好
Have a seat.
坐
Make them nice and clean.
擦干净点啊
You got it.
好嘞
Hand me that newspaper.
报纸给我一下
It's okay,
没事儿
no need to be nervous.
不用紧张
Takagi.
高木
Right now?
现在马上吗
We are one step away.
明明只差一步了
Did you not tell Mr. Nakamura?
你没跟里见先生说吗
We need to get Meng Duoci's whereabouts
一定得从那女的嘴里
from that policewoman!
问出孟多慈的下落
Are you ordering me?
你是命令我的吗
Return to
现在马上
the Marine Corps headquarters
撤回海军陆战队的
right now.
司令部
Takagi!
高木
Hello?
喂
Mr. Nakamura,
里见先生
Takagi Tamaki has acted on his own.
高木环已经擅自行动了
He's planning to approach
他打算再去找
that policewoman again.
那个女警察
Stop him immediately.
马上阻止他
If the police traced it to the diner,
警察既然查到料理店
they might track it back to the school.
就有可能顺着查到学校
Tell him to cease all operations
让他停止一切行动
and return
现在就回
to the Marine Corps headquarters now.
海军陆战队司令部
Is that him?
是他吗
Yes.
是
Captain,
队长
should we make a move?
我们要行动吗
Not in the Japanese quarter.
日侨区
Hold off for now. Follow him.
先不动手 跟着他
What's wrong?
怎么了
Captain.
队长
This is our first time here.
我们第一次来这个地方
We can't just barge in.
不能硬闯
Right,
对
the killer
有可能凶手
could be lurking
就猫在某个地方
anywhere here.
看着我们
Cowards!
缩头乌龟
He was
之前还
all over Luo Minmin before,
死追着骆珉敏不放
now he's scared.
今天怂了
He probably saw our numbers
估计看我们人多
and got scared off.
不敢出来了
Captain,
队长
should we ask the theater staff
要不要找剧院的人
to turn on the lights?
把灯开开
Turning on the lights might scare him away.
把灯开开这不跑了吗
So, what do we do?
那我们怎么办啊
I can lure him out.
我可以把他引出来
What are you thinking?
你干什么
He's looking for me.
他要找的人是我
If I walk out alone,
要是我单独出行
I can draw him out.
就可以把他引出来
That's too risky.
这太危险了
He doesn't know where Qiushi is yet.
他现在没有秋实的下落
He likely won't kill me right away.
应该不会轻易杀掉我
He knows the school
他也知道这个学校
has been compromised.
已经暴露了
If he misses this chance,
错过这一次
he won't get another.
他就没有机会了
Captain,
队长
I can do this.
我可以
Minmin,
珉敏
you enter through the side hall.
一会儿你从小厅走
Yuansheng, follow her.
向远生跟着她
You two, cover the door.
你们两个守门口
Erbai, you take that side.
二白从那儿走
Understood.
明白
Be careful.
小心点
I'm on your back.
我会一直跟着你